Guide to the Hispanic Communities Documentation Project records and oral histories ARC.032
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 1: Publicized oral histories, 1988-1989
  - Gaston, Mariana, 1988 December 15; 1989.004.16
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Cuba; Havana (Cuba); New York (N.Y.); Miami (Fla.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Cuban Americans; Education; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Multiculturalism; Musicians; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Spanish language
  - Duran, Amantina, 1989 March 28; 1989.004.17
    Amantina Durán originated from the district of Loma Prieta, San José de las Matas, Dominican Republic. After arriving in New York City, she first lived in Manhattan and moved to the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn, where she resided when the interview took place in 1989. Durán attended the Church of the Transfiguration along with many nearby Dominican Americans. With her two daughters in college, she studied English at Solidaridad Humana, a school on Manhattan's Lower East Side.
    In the interview, Amantina Durán names her motivations for moving; one of her reasons for living in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn is its proximity to the Church of the Transfiguration. She states that many Dominicans from her hometown also live nearby. At the church, a group from Loma Prieta and from other small neighboring towns meet on a regular basis. They contribute to a fund that offers financial aid to needy members. Durán discusses the Church's Nuestros Ninos Day Care Center, where she sent her daughters, thus allowing her to go to work in small factories in lower Manhattan. She discusses changes in Williamsburg; once heavily Puerto Rican, but populated instead by those of Dominican and Mexican heritages at the time of the 1989 interview. Finally, she talks about the problems of drugs, gentrification pressures, and conflicts between Williamsburg's Latino and Jewish communities. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Dominican Americans; New York (N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Day care centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Dominican Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; English as a second language; Ethnic identity; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Language and languages; Puerto Ricans; Transfiguration Roman Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Guzman, J.R., 1988 August 30; 1989.004.18
    J.R. (José Rafael) Guzmán was born in Monte Christi, in the north of the Dominican Republic. He came to the United States as a child, as a result of his mother's political activity against the Trujillo regime. They had first gone to Mayaguez, Puerto Rico in 1952, where the family had relatives, and then moved to upper Manhattan in the mid-1950s. Guzmán lived at 135th Street and Broadway until 1965. At the time that the area became heavily populated with Dominicans, Guzmán left the neighborhood and moved to the Bronx. While studying engineering at the University of Puerto Rico in 1967, he was drafted and sent to Vietnam, although not yet a United States citizen. After his release from the Army, he attended Lehman College, where he studied art. While still at Lehman, he took a job as a graphic artist, and in 1978 he started his own company. At the time of the 1988 interview, he worked with Roman and Tannenholz, an advertising company in Manhattan. Guzmán moved to the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1982, where he owned a home that he renovated himself. Some years before this interview, he obtained citizenship.
    In this interview, J.R. (José Rafael) Guzmán recalls events and places leading up to his life in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. Among his memories of the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan are the different ethnic gangs. The Puerto Ricans had one, but the Dominicans did not. He discusses the ethnic composition of the neighborhood, as well as the influx of Dominicans and other Latinos into the neighborhood. He mentions that the older store owners are usually Puerto Rican, but that the younger owners, especially of bodegas and record shops, are often Dominican. He senses some animosity between the two groups. As a member of the Sunset Park Restoration Committee, Guzmán is involved in community affairs but observes the lack of Latinos in that committee. He feels that Sunset Park will remain Latino because of the large number of Latino/a home owners. Interview conducted by Morton Marks.
    Bodegas |z New York (State) |z New York; Dominican Americans; Hispanic Americans -- New York (State) -- New York; Music |z New York (State) |z New York; Musicians; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race identity; Spanish language; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 |x Veterans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Dominican Republic; New York (N.Y.); Puerto Rico; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
  - Castillo, Diogenes, 1989 May 4; 1989.004.19
    Born in the Dominican Republic in the early 1970s, Diógenes Castillo was a student at Bushwick High School when this 1989 interview took place. He first lived on Manhattan's Lower East Side in the mid-1980s before moving to the Bushwick neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    In this interview, Diógenes Castillo describes what occupies his time as a high school student, including his work in a bodega in the Bushwick neighborhood of Brooklyn. He talks about that neighborhood's Latino Caribbean culture, including Casa Borínquen, a dance club. Interview conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Dominican Republic; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Bodegas |z New York (State) |z New York; Dominican Americans; English as a second language; High school students |z New York (State) |z New York |x Conduct of life; Hispanic Americans -- New York (State) -- New York; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Music |z New York (State) |z New York; Nightclubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Andon, Esperanza, 1989 January 4; 1989.004.20
    Esperanza Andón is from Piaxtla, Puebla, Mexico. She and her husband immigrated to New York in 1972, and found work in Brooklyn. They then began to bring their children from Mexico. Andón founded a marathon race in honor of the Virgin of Guadalupe. She is also a cook, and prepares regional Mexican specialties at home and distributes them house to house in the Mexican sections of Brooklyn, and at the Mexican American community's sports events at a park in the Red Hook neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    In the interview, Esperanza Andón discusses the early days of her life in Brooklyn, when there were few Mexican products in the bodegas, and she had to travel to Casa Moneo on 14th Street in Manhattan. She recalls that in 1978, Mexican products began to appear in a Dominican-owned bodega on Myrtle and Franklin Avenues, and then in Mexican neighborhoods all over the borough. Andón describes in detail the origin of Brooklyn's Guadalupe Day ceremonies, beginning at the Guadalupe church in Manhattan, then through a series of Brooklyn churches, before finally finding a home at All Saints Church in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn. She describes the regional costumes, including the china poblana and inditos, worn in the Guadalupe procession. Andón also recounts her inspiration to develop a marathon race; her way of keeping a promise to the Virgin of Guadalupe, after having health and immigration status issues. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Mexico; New York (N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Bodegas |z New York (State) |z New York; Churches -- New York (State) -- New York; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic identity; Festivals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; International cooking; Mexican Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Music |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Running races; All Saints Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Soriano, Amado, 1989 February 12; 1989.004.21
    Amado Soriano was born in Piaxtla, a village in the state of Puebla, Mexico. His father was a school teacher. Soriano moved to Mexico City in 1965 with his brother and worked in a publicity agency. He came to New York City in 1971, at first living with friends in the South Bronx. He found work in a private restaurant in the Wall Street area of Manhattan (where he continued to work when the interview took place in 1989). In 1971, he moved to the Borough Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. Soriano is an active member of several important Mexican organizations in Brooklyn; including la Sociedad Guadalupana, dedicated to organizing the services for Mexico's patron saint and held every December, and the Comite Pro-Construccion Capilla Cristo Rey en Piaxtla, a group raising funds to build a chapel in his hometown in Puebla.
    In the interview, Amado Soriano recalls many of his biographical details; from his youth in Piaxtla, Puebla, Mexico and as a young man in Mexico City and New York City. He speaks about the Virgin of Guadalupe ceremonies. Soriano details his son's participation, in that he dances with Los Tecuanes, a group of masked dancers who perform on the Virgin of Guadalupe's day. Soriano recounts the history of these dances, from their Mexican Indian origins, as well as the origins of the town of Piaxtla. Finally, he describes the growth of the Mexican community in Brooklyn. The interview closes with a reading of a composition, "Saludo Guadalupano." Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Borough Park (New York, N.Y.); Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Mexico; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Churches -- New York (State) -- New York; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Dancers |z New York (State) |z New York; Ethnic identity; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Festivals; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; International cooking; Mexican Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Music |z New York (State) |z Kings County; All Saints Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Rojas, Miguel, 1989 March 16; 1989.004.22
    Miguel Rojas was born in Piaxtla, Puebla, Mexico, and came to Brooklyn in 1980. His father came to New York in the late sixties, and founded the first Mexican bakery in the borough, located in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn. His family were among the first Mexicans to come to that neighborhood. The Rojas bakery makes several kinds of Mexican breads.
    In the interview, Miguel Rojas recalls the major biographical details of his life. He looks back on the family immigrating to New York City and relocating from Manhattan to Brooklyn. He identifies quality of life issues as they apply to the Latino/a community; schools, small business, food, and job opportunities. Rojas details the business model of his bakery; they sell not only to repartidores—people who sell Mexican food door to door—but also to bodegas in Mexican neighborhoods. He describes the distribution of the Mexican community in Brooklyn. He discusses how the work is shared by his family members in the bakery, and how difficult it is to study at Pace University while managing a growing business. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Mexico; New York (N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Bakeries |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bakery employees |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Dominican Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic identity; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; International cooking; Mexican Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County
  - Aguilar, Jose, 1989 February 11; 1989.004.23
    José Aguilar left El Salvador in 1980, when a relative was killed in the civil war and he began to fear for his own safety. He came to New York City via Mexico, and lived first in the Far Rockaway neighborhood of Queens. Aguilar found work in the Greenpoint neighborhood of Brooklyn, but was picked up by immigration authorities and jailed. His fine was paid by a sister of the Church of the Transfiguration, and he was released. The church helped him find work, and his first job was at a summer camp in Upstate New York. Aguilar found an apartment in "Los Sures'' in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn, not far from the Church of the Transfiguration.
    In the interview, José Aguilar examines the difficulties of attending school to learn English while working and trying to survive economically. He speaks of the illusions that many Salvadorans have that they will live in the Manhattan skyscrapers they have seen in pictures, but end up in poor areas of Brooklyn. But in spite of difficulties, he feels that the community of Salvadorans that has fully formed near the church provides a support system that makes life more bearable for him. Aguilar observes that the Church of the Transfiguration has helped so many Central Americans, and as a result, many people arriving from there head directly to the church. Interview in Spanish conducted by Lucia Rodriguez.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); El Salvador; Far Rockaway (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Churches -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Dominican Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic relations; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Mexican Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Salvadorans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Transfiguration Roman Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Ramirez, Mario, 1989 February 2; 1989.004.24
    Mario Ramirez is from the town of Armenia, not far from the capital of El Salvador. His mother, fearing for his safety because of the civil war, sent him to Guatemala when he was only fourteen. This began an odyssey that was to last many years and that took Ramirez all through Central America, Mexico and the United States, often just a few steps ahead of the immigration police and sometimes living off the land. At the age of twenty, he found his way to Brooklyn and the Church of the Transfiguration. Ramirez found work in a factory, and then as a sexton in another Brooklyn church, where he also lives. When the interview took place in 1989, he was studying to be a building superintendent.
    In the interview, Mario Ramirez recalls his travels, many jobs, and hardships along the way. As a refugee from civil war in El Salvador, Ramirez remembers first entering the United States in Texas. He went back to El Salvador, but the civil war had worsened, and his mother sent him to Mexico City where a brother-in-law was living. He tells of crossing once again into Texas, and eventually finding work in the oil fields of Louisiana, and in agricultural work in the American South. He journeyed back and forth across the United States for six years. Ramirez recounts being helped by a priest at the Church of the Transfiguration when he arrived in Brooklyn. In the late 1980s, he made a trip back to visit El Salvador, and by then was established enough to help his family financially. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); California; El Salvador; Mexico; Texas; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Church work with immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Churches -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Salvadorans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Sports -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Transfiguration Roman Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Guzman, Julia, 1989 March 6; 1989.004.25
    Born in Mexicanos, a suburb of San Salvador, El Salvador, Julia Guzmán was proprietor of Los Churros Restaurant on lower Fifth Avenue in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn. She left El Salvador in 1973, and had originally planned to join her relatives in California. However, a friend convinced her to come to Brooklyn. In 1987, after having worked in Brooklyn factories and as a housekeeper, Guzmán decided to open a Salvadoran restaurant. Los Churros became a popular gathering spot. At the time of the interview in 1989, Guzmán was planning to move the restaurant to a larger space within Brooklyn.
    In the interview, Julia Guzmán recounts her early days on Bergen Street in Brooklyn, when there were few Salvadorans in the area. She speaks of the growth of the Salvadoran community in Brooklyn, and especially in Jamaica, Queens. She also discusses the political situation in her country, and the difficulties the civil war there has created. Guzmán describes the success of her Los Churros Restaurant; especially on weekends, when a large, pan-Hispanic crowd comes to eat the Salvadoran specialties and to dance to live music. Finally, she recounts the story of how her hometown of Mexicanos received its name. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); California; El Salvador; El Salvador -- History -- Civil War; Mexico; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; International cooking; Music |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Restaurateurs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Salvadorans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Los Churros Restaurant (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Rosales, Ana, 1989 March 16; 1989.004.26
    Born in Juigalpa, Nicaragua, Ana Rosales first came to Brooklyn in 1974 when her first husband—a military officer—was sent by the Somoza government to study at Pratt Institute. She returned to Nicaragua in 1978, on the eve of the Sandinista revolution. Her husband was in the interior fighting the guerrillas when Rosales decided to leave the country; afraid of what the revolutionaries might do to the wife of an Army officer. After many immigration and travel hurdles she arrived in Miami, where she was assisted by the Red Cross and Miami Cuban Americans. Rosales then came to the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn with her three small children and stayed with friends. By 1989 she remarried, and was living with her family in a church-owned building near the Church of the Transfiguration in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    In the interview, Ana Rosales recalls the major biographical details of her life. She remembers her youth in Nicaragua, as well as her challenging attempts to flee the country during wartime. Her path included being stuck in Managua, crossing into Honduras, returning to Managua, flying out of El Salvador, and entering the United States. Rosales recounts her family's adapting to the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn. In desperate financial straits, she was given the address of the Church of the Transfiguration by a social worker. She tells of her meeting with Sister Peggy Walsh and other church people, who helped her by providing an apartment in "Los Sures'' within the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn, and encouraged her to find work. Rosales speaks about working in a clothing factory, and attending Boricua College to study English. She also describes getting a position as a teacher's aide at a day care center. Interview in Spanish conducted by Morton Marks.
    Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); El Salvador; Guatemala; Nicaragua; Nicaragua -- History -- Revolution, 1979; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Day care centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; English as a second language; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Nicaraguan Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Public welfare |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Transfiguration Roman Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Vega, Francisco, 1989 March 25; 1989.004.27
    Francisco Vega was born in Granada, Nicaragua, and later moved to the capital of Managua. He was involved there with a number of businesses, including factory supplies. Under suspicion from the Sandinista government of having been in the Somoza army, he left Nicaragua in 1985, sponsored by a friend who lived in Brooklyn. After staying with this friend at first, he moved to Queens, where he lived for three years before moving again to the Greenpoint neighborhood of Brooklyn. He resided there when the interview took place in 1989. He was able to find a job with a company that cleans restaurant equipment. He then set up a similar company of his own, where he employed many Latino/a workers.
    In the interview, Francisco Vega recalls the immigration experience that makes up a major part of his life story. He speaks of his pride at the fact that, having gone through a period of great hardship, including some weeks when he lived on the street, he is now self-employed and doing well financially. He describes his attempts to bring his children from Nicaragua, and to settle his problems with the immigration authorities. He also speaks of his relatives who live in the Nicaraguan communities in San Francisco and Los Angeles, California. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); California; Greenpoint (New York, N.Y.); Mexico; Nicaragua; Queens (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; International cooking; Nicaraguan Americans -- Employment -- New York (State) -- New York; Nicaraguan Americans |z New York (State) |z New York
  - Lopez, Jorge, 1989 April 9; 1989.004.28
    Jorge Lopez is from Livingston, on the Caribbean coast of Guatemala. He emigrated in 1970, and came to live in Brooklyn, where he had some relatives. Lopez worked in customs in his port city of Livingston. After arriving in the States, he first found work as a garage mechanic in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn, and then went to work on the borough's docks. He was also an active member of St. Michael's Church.
    In the interview, Jorge Lopez discusses the Guatemalan colonies in Brooklyn, Jamaica, Queens, and New Jersey, where there are large Guatemalan communities. He describes a Guatemalan club that prepares for the Hispanidad Parade in Manhattan every year, and speaks of the numerous Guatemalan soccer leagues; who play other soccer leagues of the Latino Brooklyn community. He describes his work at the docks on Brooklyn's waterfront, and talks of the growth of the Guatemalan community in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. According to Lopez, this growth was aided by the arrival of Mexican produce since Guatemalan cuisine resembles Mexican cooking. Interview in Spanish conducted by Marcelo Herman.